Guide to the Educators and Librarians Collection, 1846-1953
Department of Special Collections
Educators and Librarians Collection,
1846-1953
Special Collections M130
.25 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions:
None.
Provenance:
Received from various gifts and purchases.
SCOPE AND CONTENT
This collection includes letters, postcards, bills, and clippings, representing persons in the fields of education and librarianship. Of note are the 181 items pertaining to William James, including 164 letters from James to F. C. S. Schiller discussing pragmatism, humanism, and personal matters.
ADDED ENTRIES
Bowman, Isaiah, 1878-1950.; Compton, Karl Taylor, 1887-1954.; Conant, James Bryant, 1893-; Cranch, Christopher Pearse, 1813-1892.; Dodds, Harold Willis, 1889-; Eliot, Charles William, 1834-1926.; Hadley, Arthur Twining, 1856-1930.; Hart, James David, 1911-; Hutchins, Robert Maynard, 1899-; James, Alice H.; James, William, 1842-1910.; Kelly, Robert L.; Lowell, Abbott Lawrence, 1856-1943.; M'Taggart, John Ellis, 1866-1925.; Moton, Robert Russa, 1867-1940.; Pearson, Edmund Lester, 1880-1937.; Peirce, Charles S. (Charles Sanders), 1839-1914.; Phelps, William Lyon, 1865-1943.; Putnam, Herbert, 1861-; Rodgers, Oliver.; Schiller, F. C. S. (Ferdinand Canning Scott), 1864-1937.; Scudder, Vida Dutton, 1861-1954.; Seymour, Charles, 1885-1963.; Stephans, Henry Morse, 1857-1919.; Strong, Charles Augustus, 1862-1940.; Veblen, Thorstein, 1857-1929.
CONTAINER LIST
- Armstrong, A. J. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - T.L.S. to Mrs. M. C. Sloss, 1953 Sept. 28
- Bowman, Isaiah [1878-] (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - T.L.S. to R. L. Wilbur, 1937 Mar. 22
- Compton, Karl Taylor [1887-1954] (physicist) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - T.L.S. to R. L. Wilbur, 1937 Mar. 22
- Conant, James Bryant [1893-] (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - T.L.S. to R. L. Wilbur, 1937 Mar. 23
- Coulter, Edith M. (Box 1, Folder 4b)
  - Christmas card, n.d.
- Dodds, Harold Willis [1889-] (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - T.L.S. to R. L. Wilbur, 1937 Mar. 22
- Eliot, Charles William [1834-1926] (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Fragment to Godrey Morse, autograph value only, n.d.
- Fowle, Priscilla H. (Box 1, Folder 6a)
  - T.L.S. to Helen Sutliff, 1919 Apr. 10
- Gates, Thomas S. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - T.L.S. to R. L. Wilbur, 1937 Mar. 23
- Hadley, Arthur Twining [1856-1930] (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Autograph only
- Hart, James D. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1. T.N.S. to Stanford English Club, verso, 1931 Oct. 27;A.L.S. Barbara F. Gibbs to "Grace Margaret" 1931 Oct. 23
  - 2. T.L.S. to Mr. Craig, 1936 Mar. 3
- Harvard College (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1. Receipted bill of N. Webb, 1946
  - 2. Receipt (perhaps not Harvard), 1898
- Hutchins, Robert Maynard [1899-] (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - T.L.S. to R. L. Wilbur, 1937 Mar. 24
- James, Alice H. (Mrs. William) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1. A.L.S. to F. Canning S. Schiller with note by Mr. William James, 1897 Oct. 18
  - 2. A.L.S. to Mr. Schiller, 1899 Nov. 10
  - 3. A.L.S. to Mr. Schiller - William's illness, 1910 July 28
  - 4. A.L.S. to Mr. Schiller - William's death in August, with cvr., 1910 Dec. 9
  - 5. A.L.S. to Mr. Schiller, 1911 June 23
  - 6. A.L.S. to Mr. Schiller, 1911 Aug. 5
  - 7. A.L.S. to Mr. Schiller, with cvr. 1912 Mar. 7
  - 8. A.L.S. to Mr. Schiller, with cvr. 1912 July 22
  - 9. A.L.S. to Mr. Schiller, with cvr. - Death of Henry James, 1916 Mar. 14
  - 10. A.L.S. to Mr. Schiller, 1916 July 10
  - 11. A.L.S. to Mr. Schiller, [1916] Aug. 17
  - 12. A.L.S. to Mr. Schiller, 1917 Mar. 7
- James, William. Letters, 1896-1900 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 1. James to [F. Canning S.] Schiller, A.L.S. 1896 Jan. 9
  - 2. James to [F. Canning S.] Schiller, A.L.S. 1896 June 9
  - 3. James to [F. Canning S.] Schiller, A.L.S. 1896 Sept. 15
  - 4. James to [F. Canning S.] Schiller, T.L.S. 1896 Oct. 17
  - 5. James to [F. Canning S.] Schiller, T.L.S. 1897 Mar. 6
  - 6. James to [F. Canning S.] Schiller, A.L.S. 1897 Apr. 22
  - 7. James to [F. Canning S.] Schiller, T.L.S. 1897 June 5
  - 8. James to [F. Canning S.] Schiller, A.L.S. 1897 Aug. 19
  - 9. James to [F. Canning S.] Schiller, A.L.S., with cvr., 1897 Oct. 23
  - 10. [D.] S. Miller to Schiller, A.L.S. 1899 [Jan.] 24
  - 11. James to Schiller, T.L.S. with autograph postcript & note by Schiller, 1899 Jan. 27
  - 12. James to Schiller, A.L.S. & cvr., 1899 May 19
  - 13. James to Schiller, A.L.S. 1899 Oct. 11
  - 14. [Schiller] to James, A.L. not signed, 1899 Oct. 12
  - 15. James to Schiller, A.L.S. 1899 Oct. 19
  - 16. James to Schiller. Letter dictated to, handwritten, and signed by Alice H. James, 1899 Nov. 17
  - 17. James to Schiller, T.L.S. 1900 Jan. 9
  - 18. James to Schiller, P.C.S. 1900 Mar. 6
  - 19. James to Schiller, A.P.C.S. 1900 Mar. 15
  - 20. James to Schiller, A.P.C.S. 1900 Mar. 30
  - 21. James to Schiller. Dictated, handwritten postcard, 1900 Apr. 6
  - 22. James to Schiller, A.P.C.S. 1900 July 28
  - 23. James to Schiller, A.L.S., [1900] Sept. 30
  - 24. Unknown to William James. Fragment of a letter with two quotes from Montesquieu, 1900 Sept. 30
  - 25. James to Schiller, A.L.S. & cvr. 1900 Oct. 6
  - 26. James to Grace [Norton?], A.L.S. 1900 Oct. 21
  - 27. James to Schiller, A.P.C.S. 1900 Dec. 28
- James, William. Letters 1901-1902 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 1. James to [F.C.S.] Schiller, A.L.S. & cvr. 1901 Jan. 1
  - 2. James to [F.C.S.] Schiller, A.P.C.S. 1901 Mar. 3
  - 3. James to [F.C.S.] Schiller, A.P.C.S. 1901 Mar. 6
  - 4. James to [F.C.S.] Schiller, A.P.C.S. 1901 Apr. 5
  - 5. James to [F.C.S.] Schiller, A.L.S. 1901 Apr. 13
  - 6. James to [F.C.S.] Schiller, A.L.S. 1901 Apr. 27
  - 7. James to [F.C.S.] Schiller, A.L.S. 1901 Apr. 30
  - 8. James to [F.C.S.] Schiller, A.P.C.S. 1901 May 5
  - 9. James to [F.C.S.] Schiller, A.L.S. 1901 May 8
  - 10. James to [F.C.S.] Schiller, A.L.S. 1901 May 10
  - 11. James to [F.C.S.] Schiller, A.L.S. 1901 June 29
  - 12. James to [F.C.S.] Schiller, A.P.C.S. 1901 July 5
  - 13. Unknown to William James, fragment of a letter 1901 Dec. 23
  - 14. James to [F.C.S.] Schiller, A.L.S. 1902 Feb. 25
  - 15. James to [F.C.S.] Schiller, A.L.S. [1902] Mar. 24
  - 16. James to [F.C.S.] Schiller, A.L.S. 1902 Apr. 18
  - 17. James to [F.C.S.] Schiller, A.L.S. [1902] Apr. 20
  - 18. James to [F.C.S.] Schiller, A.L.S. & cvr. 1902 Apr. 24
  - 19. James to [F.C.S.] Schiller, A.L.S. 1902 Apr. 24
  - 20. James to [F.C.S.] Schiller, A.L.S. 1902 Apr. 27
  - 21. James to [F.C.S.] Schiller, A.L.S. [1902] May 2
  - 22. James to [F.C.S.] Schiller, A.P.C.S. 1902 May 8
  - 23. James to [F.C.S.] Schiller, A.L.S. [1902] May 17
  - 24. James to [F.C.S.] Schiller, A.P.C.S. 1902 May 17
  - 25. James to [F.C.S.] Schiller, A.L.S. 1902 May 29
  - 26. James to [F.C.S.] Schiller, A.L.S. [1902] June 8
  - 27. James to [F.C.S.] Schiller, A.L.S. & cvr. 1902 Aug. 6
  - 28. James to [F.C.S.] Schiller, A.P.C.S. 1902 Aug. 29
  - 29. James to [F.C.S.] Schiller, A.L.S. & cvr. 1902 Nov. 27
- James, William. Letters 1903-1904 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - 1. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S., 1903 Apr. 8
  - 2. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.P.C.S., 1903 Apr. 12
  - 3. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S., 1903 May 1
  - 4. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.P.C.S., 1903 July 5
  - 5. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.P.C.S., 1903 July 27
  - 6. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.P.C.S., 1903 Sept. 4
  - 7. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S. & cvr., 1903 Sept. 9
  - 8. F. C. S. Schiller to W. James, A.L.S., 1903 Sept. 25
  - 9. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S., 1903 Nov. 16
  - 10. F. C. S. Schiller to James, A.L. not signed, 1903 Nov. 24
  - 11. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.P.C.S., 1903 Dec. 16
  - 12. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S., 1904 Feb. 1
  - 13. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S. & cvr., 1904 June 12
  - 14. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.P.C.S., 1904 July 7
  - 15. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.P.C.S., 1904 July [15?]
  - 16. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S., 1904 Aug. 9
  - 17. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.P.C.S., 1904 Aug.
  - 18. James to Prof. G. F. Stout, A.P.C.S., 1904 Aug.
  - 19. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S. & cvr., 1904 Sept. 2
  - 20. F. C. S. Schiller to James, A.L. not signed, 1904 [Sept. 2]
  - 21. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S, 1904 Sept. 14
  - 22. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S., 1904 Sept. 30
  - 23. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S., 1904 Oct. 9
  - 24. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S., 1904 Oct. 26
- James, William. Letters 1905-1906 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 1. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S. & cvr., 1905 Jan. 23
  - 2. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S., 1905 Feb. 7
  - 3. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S., 1905 Mar. 2
  - 4. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S., 1905 May 12
  - 5. C.S. Peirce to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S., 1905 May 13
  - 6. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S., 1905 May 18
  - 7. Charles Snaders Peirce to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S., 1905 May 23
  - 8. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S. & cvr., 1905 [May 27]
  - 9. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S., 1905 May 28
  - 10. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.P.C.S., 1905 June 2
  - 11. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.P.C.S., 1905 June 16
  - 12. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.P.C.S., 1905 June 23
  - 13. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.P.C.S., 1905 July [20]
  - 14. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S. & cvr., 1905 July 21
  - 15. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.P.C.S., 1905 Aug. [17]
  - 16. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S., 1906 Jan. 16
  - 17. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S., 1906 Jan. 30
  - 18. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.P.C.S., 1906 Feb. 17
  - 19. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S. & cvr., 1906 Feb. 24
  - 20. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S., 1906 Apr. 7
  - 21. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S., 1906 May 20
  - 22. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S., 1906 Aug. 3
  - 23. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S., 1906 Aug. 24
  - 24. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.P.C.S., 1906 Nov. 25
  - 25. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.P.C.S., 1906 Nov. 25
- James, William. Letters, 1907-1908 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - 1. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.P.C.S., 1907 Jan. 4
  - 2. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.P.C.S., 1907 Feb. 20
  - 3. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.P.C.S., 1907 Mar. 22
  - 4. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S., 1907 Apr. 19
  - 5. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S. & cvr., 1907 May 18
  - 6. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.P.C.S., 1907 June 13
  - 7. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L. fragment, 1907July 15
  - 8. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.P.C.S., 1907 Aug. 31
  - 9. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L fragment., 1907 Oct. 16
  - 10. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.P.C.S., 1907 Oct. 17
  - 11. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.P.C.S., 1907 Oct. 22
  - 12. James to F. C. S. Schiller, clip (Nov. 3) & cvr. [Nov. 16] 1907 [Nov. 7]
  - 13. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.P.C.S., [1908 Jan. 17?]
  - 14. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S. & cvr., 1908 Jan. 26
  - 15. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S. & cvr., 1908 Jan. 27
  - 16. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.P.C.S., 1908 Feb. 22
  - 17. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.P.C.S., 1908 Mar. 2
  - 18. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S. & cvr., 1908 Mar. 20
  - 19. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.P.C.S., 1908 Apr. 18
  - 20. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S., 1908 June 15 or 16
  - 21. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.P.C.S., 1908 June 17
  - 22. C. A. Strong to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S., 1908 June 30
  - 23. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.P.C.S., 1908 July 6
  - 24. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S., 1908 Aug. 4
  - 25. James to Mrs. Cobden-Sanderson, A.L.S., 1908 Aug. 11
  - 26. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S., 1908 Sept. 15
  - 27. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S., 1908 Sept. 20
  - 28. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S., 1908 Sept. 23
  - 29. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.P.C.S., 1908 Oct. 5
  - 30. F. C. S. Schiller to [C. A.] Strong, A.L.S., [1908]
  - 31. [Schiller notes on Strong], 7 pp., 1908 [May?]
- James, William. Letters 1980, 1909-1910 and undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 1. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S., 1909 Jan. 17
  - 2. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S., 1909 Mar. 10
  - 3. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S. & cvr., 1909 Apr. 27
  - 4. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.P.C.S., 1909 May 15
  - 5. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S., 1909 June 22
  - 6. Glasgow Herald clip. & cvr., 1909 June 25
  - 7. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S. & cvr., 1909 July 17
  - 8. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.P.C.S., 1909 July 20
  - 9. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.P.C.S., 1909 July 23
  - 10. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S. & cvr., 1909 Aug. 4
  - 11. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S., fragment, [1909 Aug.]
  - 12. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S., 1909 Aug. 14
  - 13. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S., 1909 Aug. 22
  - 14. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S., 1909 Sept. 5
  - 15. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S., 1909 Oct. 30
  - 16. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S. & cvr., 1909 Nov. 6
  - 17. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S., 1909 Dec. 4
  - 18. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.P.C.S., 1909 Dec. 5
  - 19. James' statement, typescript with ms. corrections, 1908
  - 20. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S., 1910 Jan. 5
  - 21. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S., 1910 Jan. 16
  - 22. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.P.C.S., 1910 Feb. 18
  - 23. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S. & cvr., 1910 Feb. 24
  - 24. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S., 1910 Apr. 8
  - 25. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S., 1910 Apr. 22
  - 26. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S., 1910 Apr. 27
  - 27. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S., 1910 May 4
  - 28. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S., 1910 May 9
  - 29. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.P.C.S., 1910 May 20
  - 30. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.P.C.S., 1910 May 29
  - 31. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.P.C.S., 1910 [May 31]
  - 32a. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.P.C.S., 1910 June 12
  - 32b. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.P.C.S., 1910 June 22
  - 33. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.P.C.S., 1910 Aug. 8
  - 34. James to Mrs. Wilmarth, A.L.S., [1905?] June 26
  - 35. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.P.C.S., n.y. Oct. 14
  - 36. James to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S., n.d.
  - 37. James to F. C. S. Schiller, L.S., dictated, n.d.
  - 38. Margaret-James Porter to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S., n.y. Jan. 11
  - 39. Margaret-James Porter to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S., n.y. Mar. 20
  - 40. Margaret-James Porter to F. C. S. Schiller, A.L.S., n.d.
  - 41. Christopher Pearse Cranch. Fragment or quote on M'Taggart, n.d.
  - 42. John Ellis M'Taggart. Fragment of letter, n.d.
  - 43. Clip, n.d.
- Kelly, Robert L. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - T.L.S. to R. L. Wilbur, 1937 Mar. 23
- Lowell, Abbott Lawrence (1856-1943) (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - A.L.S. to [H. B.] Learned, 1900 Jan 14
- Moton, Robert Russa (1867-1940) (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - T.L.S. to R. L. Wilbur, 1930 May 5
- Pearson, Edmund Lester (Box 1, Folder 21a)
  - T.L.S. to Editor, Harvard Graduate Magazine, 1910 Oct. 10
- Phelps, William Lyon (1865-1943) (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - A.L.S. to "Dear Laura," 1939 [May?] 28
- Putnam, Herbert (1861- ) (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - A.L.S. to Frederick E. Brasch with photo of bust by Brenda Putnam, 1950 Sept. 25
  - A.L.S. to Frederick E. Brasch with cvr. and clip of 90th birthday, 1951 Oct. 17
- Rodgers, Oliver (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - T.L.S. to [R. L. Wilbur], 1918 Dec. 12
- Scudder, Vida Dutton (1861- ) (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - T.L.S. to Mrs. M. C. Sloss, 1930 July 7
- Seymour, Charles (1885- ) (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - T.L.S. to R. L. Wilbur, 1937 May 11
- Stephens, Henry Morse (1857-1919) (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - 1. A.L.S. to Mrs. Sloss, 1905 June 2
  - 2. A.L.S. to Mrs. Sloss with cvr., 1914 May 27
- Sandoe, James (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - 1. A.P.C.S. Maurice Dale Colbourne to Sandoe, 1934 Oct. 4
  - 2. T.L. to Patricia Collinge, 1938 Feb. 20
  - 3. T.L.S. & cvr. P. Collinge to Sandoe, 1938 Mar. 21
  - 4. T.L.S. P. Collinge to Sandoe, 1938 Oct. 13
  - 5. Typescript of radio script "Balcony Scene" by P. Collinge enclosed in above, 1938 Feb. 20
  - 6. T.L. to P. Collinge, 1938 Oct. 16